Guide to the Archives of Irish America Collection on the McNulty Family AIA.051
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Collection on the McNulty Family
1907-2011
1928-1955
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grogan, Patricia Ann
Grogan, James Peter
Barfoot, Monty
AIA.051
15.5 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 record carton, 2 custom boxes, 6 flat boxes, and 5 oversize folders.
728.8 Megabytes in 150 computer files.
77 sound discs
4 audiocassettes
1 sound tape reels
The Archives of Irish America Collection on the McNulty Family chronicles the career of the Irish American performers known as the McNulty Family. The McNulty Family were known as the "Royal Family of Irish Entertainers" and were popular in the United States, Canada, and Ireland between the 1930s and 1950s. Ann "Ma" McNulty led the trio and played accordion and melodeon; her daughter Eileen sang and danced; and her son Peter played violin and piano, sang, and danced. They also performed skits and comedy routines that sometimes accompanied their songs. The collection dates between 1907 and 2011, with the bulk of the materials from 1928 to 1955. Materials include subject files, scrapbooks created by Ann, newspaper clippings, sound recordings, sheet music, lyric books, correspondence, financial records, contracts, photographs, programs, posters, pins, Eileen McNulty's top hat, and Peter McNulty's shillelagh.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Scope and Content Note
The Archives of Irish America Collection on the McNulty Family chronicles the career of the Irish American performers known as the McNulty Family. The collection dates between 1907 and 2011, with the bulk from 1928 to 1955. The collection documents the McNulty Family's successful career as both stage performers and recording artists and consists of scrapbooks, posters, photographs, sound recordings, sheet music, lyric books, subject files, a top hat worn by Eileen McNulty and a shillelagh used by Peter McNulty in their performances, and two Blue Star Mothers pins worn by Ann during World War II. These items were assiduously collected by Ann "Ma" McNulty and document performances and other activities of her family between 1928 and 1960. The scrapbooks created by Ann contain photographs of family members, performances, and other performers with whom the McNultys appeared; flyers and advertisements for performances; clippings of The News Nest, a column written by Peter in The Advocate from 1939 to 1942 and by Ann from 1942 to 1943; and other items of interest to Ann. The posters and photographs document over 20 years of performances by the McNulty Family, including their Irish Showboat Revue and its 16 years of performances at the Brooklyn Academy of Music in Brooklyn, New York. The sheet music, lyric books, and sound recordings represent the wide range of songs performed by the McNultys. The sound recordings consist of commercial recordings and test pressings on multiple formats, including 78 RPM records; 8", 10", and 12" acetate records; 12" LPs; 7" 45 RPM records; 7" reel audio tape; audio cassettes; and MP3s. The sheet music includes both handwritten and printed arrangements, some of which were original compositions by the McNultys. The lyric books include handwritten and typed songs performed by the McNultys. The subject files contain programs and handbills documenting over 35 years of performances across New York City, New Jersey, and New England; newspaper clippings; letters to Ann and Eileen from friends and family members; Ann's naturalization documents; Peter's military records; recording contracts; royalty statements; and family trees.
Biographical Note
The McNulty Family were known as the "Royal Family of Irish Entertainers" and were popular in the United States, Canada, and Ireland between the 1930s and 1950s. Ann "Ma" McNulty led the trio and played accordion and melodeon; her daughter Eileen sang and danced; and her son Peter played violin and piano, sang, and danced. They also performed skits and comedy routines that sometimes accompanied their songs.
Ann was born Ann Burke in Kilteevan, County Roscommon, Ireland in 1887. She immigrated to the United States in 1910 and met John McNulty, who had emigrated from Drumkeeran, County Leitrim, in 1911. They were married in 1914 and lived in Attleboro, Massachusetts. They moved to New York State after Eileen was born in 1915. Peter was born in 1917. The family moved to New York City in 1923. Ann, Eileen, and Peter began performing as the McNulty Family in 1926 in New York City, but after John's death in 1928, the family began performing in larger venues, on radio, and in different cities on the East Coast. The McNulty Family created the Irish Showboat Revue, which included songs and skits, and eventually grew to include 19 performers. They appeared on many radio shows from the 1920s to the 1950s and had two weekly radio shows of their own on the local New York City station WWRL in the 1940s. Peter wrote a weekly newspaper column, The News Nest, for The Advocate between 1939 and 1942. Ann continued the column after Peter was drafted into the Army in 1942, but for less than a year. The column highlighted the social lives of the McNulty Family and other Irish American performers.
The McNulty Family continued to perform once Peter returned from active military duty in 1946, but due to his ill health they could not maintain the same schedule they had before the war. After Peter's death in 1960, Eileen and Ann continued to perform, sometimes with Eileen's son James. After her husband's death in 1968 and Ann's death in 1970, Eileen went to Ireland for training in Irish dancing and received her TCRG (Irish dance teacher certification). She returned to the US and taught Irish step dancing from 1972 to the mid-1980s. She died in 1989.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Patricia Ann Grogan and Peter James Grogan in 2010, and Monty Barfoot in 2011. The accession number associated with this gift is 2010.022.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by format or topic. Some items within this arrangement were arranged in chronological order by one of the donors.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection, with the exception of the sound recordings on disc, must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Custodial History
The Archives of Irish America Collection on the McNulty Family was assembled by Patricia Ann Grogan and James Peter Grogan from materials collected by Ann McNulty, Eileen McNulty, and Peter McNulty and donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in 2010. Sound recordings donated by Monty Barfoot in 2011 were added to the collection by Tamiment Library staff.
Related Materials
For more material on the McNulty Family in the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, see Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Commercial Recordings Collection (call phrase AIA.031.001), Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Field Recordings (call phrase AIA.031.002), and Mick Moloney Irish-American Music and Popular Culture Papers (call phrase AIA.031.003).
Irish Americans -- Music.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Irish -- Songs and music.; Irish -- Music; Entertainers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Irish American families.; Posters.; Scrapbooks.; Sheet music.; Sound recordings.; McNulty Family (Musical group); McNulty, Ann; McNulty, Eileen; McNulty, Peter; Barfoot, Monty
- Accordions, 1939, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Blauvelt Convent, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Blue Star Mothers pins, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1926-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4-11, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS002, Folder 1, Box 8, Folder 7, Box 6)
- Contracts, 1947-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1935-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Discographies, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ephemera, 1924-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Family tree, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Handbills, 1933-1962 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
- Hollywood, California, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Kilteevan, Ireland, 1941-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- McNulty, Ann, 1953-1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- McNulty, Eileen, 1968-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 23, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS002, Folder 2)
- McNulty, Peter, 1942-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Music, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3-12, Box 3, Folder 1)
- Newfoundland, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Nova Scotia, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1914-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5-15, Box 4, Folder 1-7, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS002, Folder 3, Box 6, Folder 2-4, Box 8, Folder 8)
- Posters, 1932-1982, undated (Box 7, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS002, Folder 4-5, Box 8, Folder 1-6, Box 6, Folder 5)
- Prince Edward Island, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Programs, 1926-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9-15, Box 5, Folder 1-2, Box 6, Folder 5)
- Recitations, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Recordings, 1927-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4-9, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS002, Folder 6)
- Rockaway Cafe, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Scrapbooks, 1907-1960 (Box 5, Folder 14-17, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15)
- Scripts, 1927-1944 (Box 5, Folder 11-12)
- Sheet music, 1938-1950, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-13, Box 9)
- Shillelagh, Undated (Box 11)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" commercial recordings -- Twelve Authentic Irish Folk Songs Featuring the McNulty Family, Undated (Disc XA33-755)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" commercial recordings -- A Night in Ireland with the McNulty Family, Volume 1, Undated (Disc XA33-758)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" commercial recordings -- The McNulty Family Entertains with Irish Songs, Undated (Disc XA33-759)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" commercial recordings -- A Night in Ireland with the McNulty Family, Volume 2, Undated (Disc XA33-760)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" commercial recordings -- Twelve Authentic Irish Folk Songs Featuring the McNulty Family, Undated (Disc XA33-761)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Part One"; Side B "Part Three", Undated (Disc XA33-756)
- Sound recordings -- 33 1/3 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Part Two"; Side B "Part Four", Undated (Disc XA33-757)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "When You Look in the Heart of a Shamrock", "The Darling Girl from Clare"; Side B "The Jackets Green", "The Exile of Cork", Undated (Disc XA45-60)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "There's a Sweetheart Waiting for You", "At the Close of an Irish Day"; Side B "The Toast to the 32 Counties", "The Star of Logy Bay", Undated (Disc XA45-61)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Irish Rover", "We'll Take You Back to Ireland"; Side B "Likeable, Loveable Leitrim Lad", "Hat My Father Wore on St. Patrick's Day", Undated (Disc XA45-62)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "When You're Winging Your Way Back to Ireland"; Side B "Someone's Waiting for Me Back in Ireland", Undated (Disc XA45-63)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- "At the Close of an Irish Day"; Side B "There's a Sweetheart Waiting for You", Undated (Disc XA45-64)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "Likeable Loveable Leitrim Lad"; Side B "The Hat My Father Wore Upon St. Patrick's Day", Undated (Disc XA45-65)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "Homes of Donegal"; Side B "Boys from the County Armagh", Undated (Disc XA45-66)
- Sound recordings -- 45 RPM 7" commercial recordings -- Side A "Roamin' in the Gloamin'", "When I Meet MacKay"; Side B "Breakfast in Bed on Sunday Morning", "It's Nice to Get Up in the Morning", Undated (Disc XA45-67)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 8" test pressings -- Side A "I'll Be Coming Home to You"; Side B "I'll Be Coming Home to You", 1942 (Disc XA78-2786)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Sides A and B are damaged.
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 8" test pressings -- Side A "Wee Bit of Irish" vocal and piano; Side B "Wee Bit of Irish" piano solo accompany, Undated (Disc XA78-2788)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 8" test pressings -- Side A "Wee Bit of Irish (in Me)" (vocal); Side B "Wee Bit of Irish", Undated (Disc XA78-2787)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 8" test pressings -- "Wee Bit of Irish", Peter whistling, Undated (Disc XA78-2789)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Hills of Glenswilly"; Side B "Drum Colliher", Undated (Disc XA78-2794)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Eileen"; Side B "I'll Forgive and I'll Try to Forget", Undated (Disc XA78-2795)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Moriarty, the Happy Cop"; Side B "The Old House Far Away", Undated (Disc XA78-2745)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "I'm Sighing Tonight for Killarney and You"; Side B "Back to Donegal", Undated (Disc XA78-2746)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Moon behind the Hill"; Side B "Star of the County Down", Undated (Disc XA78-2747)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Slippin' the Jig"; Side B "I Don't Care if I Do", Undated (Disc XA78-2748)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Shall My Soul Pass through Old Ireland"; Side B "The Dawning of the Morning", Undated (Disc XA78-2749)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Real Old Mountain Dew"; Side B "My Beauty of Limerick", Undated (Disc XA78-2750)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Real Old Mountain Dew"; Side B "My Beauty of Limerick", Undated (Disc XA78-2751)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Waltz Me around Again Willie"; Side B "Walker Walked Away", Undated (Disc XA78-2752)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Kerry Long Ago"; Side B "Grandfather Brian", Undated (Disc XA78-2753)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "O Son Remember My Love Today"; Side B "If You Ever Go Over", Undated (Disc XA78-2754)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Biddy Donahue"; Side B "Good-bye Johnny Dear", Undated (Disc XA78-2755)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Kellys"; Side B "McDonnell's Old Tin Roof", Undated (Disc XA78-2756)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Kellys"; Side B "McDonnell's Old Tin Roof", Undated (Disc XA78-2757)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Denny McCall"; Side B "Dunloe Fair", Undated (Disc XA78-2758)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "I Don't Work for a Living"; Side B "Amber Tresses Tied in Blue", Undated (Disc XA78-2759)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "In Old Ballymoe"; Side B "The Groves of Kilteevan", Undated (Disc XA78-2760)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "I Have a Bonnet Trimmed with Blue", "Maggie in the Woods"; Side B "Rolling Rocks of Glan", "River Meadow Reel", Undated (Disc XA78-2761)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Flowery Dell", "Miss Drury's Reel"; Side B "Chasing the Chicken", "Maid on the Green", Undated (Disc XA78-2762)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "When it's Teatime in the Meadows"; Side B "Irish Soldier Boy", Undated (Disc XA78-2763)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Hills of Glenswilly"; Side B "Drum Colliher", Undated (Disc XA78-2764)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Eileen McMahon"; Side B "The Galway Rogue", Undated (Disc XA78-2765)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "My Old Home Town"; Side B "My Own Dear Galway Bay", Undated (Disc XA78-2766)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Eileen"; Side B "I'll Forgive and I'll Try to Forget", Undated (Disc XA78-2767)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "The Stone outside Dan Murphy's Door"; Side B "The Half Door", Undated (Disc XA78-2768)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Erin's Green Shore"; Side B "The River Moy", Undated (Disc XA78-2769)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "My Sweetheart"; Side B "My Old Home Town", Undated (Disc XA78-2770)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Bedelia"; Side B "Ann Carawath", 1945 (Disc XA78-2771)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "When I Mowed Pat Murphy's Meadow"; Side B "Off to Philadelphia", 1945 (Disc XA78-2772)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Breakfast in Bed on Sunday Morning"; Side B "It's Nice to Get up in the Mornin'", Undated (Disc XA78-2773)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "Roamin' in the Gloamin'"; Side B "When I Meet Mc Kay", Undated (Disc XA78-2774)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" commercial recordings -- Side A "A Toast to the 32 Counties"; Side B "The Star of Logy Bay", Undated (Disc XA78-2775)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Haste to the Wedding", Undated (Disc XA78-2734)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "O Son Remember My Love To-day", Undated (Disc XA78-2735)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Biddy Donahue", Undated (Disc XA78-2736)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "If You Ever Go Over to Ireland", Undated (Disc XA78-2737)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Eileen O'Dair", Undated (Disc XA78-2738)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Eileen", Undated (Disc XA78-2739)
  Disc is cracked.
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Breakfast in Bed", 1954 (Disc XA78-2740)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Get Up in Mornin", 1954 (Disc XA78-2741)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "McKie", 1954 (Disc XA78-2742)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Roamin Glom", 1954 (Disc XA78-2743)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- Side A "Elileen [sic] O'Dair" Side B "Livin' the Life of Reilly", 1939 (Disc XA78-2790)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "There [sic] a Wee Bit of Irish in Me", Undated (Disc XA78-2791)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- Side A "Heaven Loves the Irish", "Oh - Oh What a Night for the Irish"; Side B "It's the Luck of the Irish", "In Love & Out Again Finnegan", 1940 (Disc XA78-2792)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- Side A "Heaven Loves the Irish", "Oh - Oh What a Night for the Irish"; Side B "Luck of the Irish", "In Love & Out Again Finnegan", Undated (Disc XA78-2744)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- Side A "Peter on violin with band"; Side B "Peter with band", Undated (Disc XA78-2793)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 10" test pressings -- "Knock at My Window", Undated (Disc XA78-2776)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Eileen O'Dair"; Side B "Riley", Undated (Disc XA78-2777)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Heart of a Shamrock"; Side B "Hill of Knock-na-Shee", Undated (Disc XA78-2778)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Queenstown Harbor"; Side B "Nell McCoy", Undated (Disc XA78-2779)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Polka"; Side B "Darling Girl from Clare", Undated (Disc XA78-2780)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Jackets Green"; Side B "Exile of Cork", Undated (Disc XA78-2781)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "106th Infantry March"; Side B "Serenade to a Mess Sergeant", "Three Day Pass", Undated (Disc XA78-2782)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "106th Infantry March"; Side B [label missing], Undated (Disc XA78-2783)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "106th Infantry March"; Side B [label missing], Undated (Disc XA78-2784)
- Sound recordings -- 78 RPM 12" test pressings -- Side A "Wire 1"; Side B "2", Undated (Disc XA78-2785)
- Sound recordings -- Audio reel, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Sound recordings -- Audio cassettes, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
- Sound recordings -- MP3s, 2010-2011 (Box Electronic records, E-records TW_AIA_51_1)
- South Roscommon Celtic Festival, 1999-2007 (Box 5, Folder 13, Box Shared Tamiment AIAOS002, Folder 5)
- Top hat, Undated (Box 12)